<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The povver of preaching. Or, the powerfull effects of the word truely preached, and rightly applyed as it was deliuered in one or moe sermons. By Iohn Traske, preacher of Gods word sometimes at Axmister in Deuon: afterwards at the Fleete in London: and now at Tillingham in Dengie hundred in Essex.</title>
            <author>Traske, John, d. ca. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838426</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838426</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2804</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13874)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2804)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1119:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The povver of preaching. Or, the powerfull effects of the word truely preached, and rightly applyed as it was deliuered in one or moe sermons. By Iohn Traske, preacher of Gods word sometimes at Axmister in Deuon: afterwards at the Fleete in London: and now at Tillingham in Dengie hundred in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Traske, John, d. ca. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Preaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2804:1"/>
            <p>THE POVVER OF PREACHING <hi>OR,</hi> THE POWERFVLL Effects of the WORD truely Preached, and rightly applyed, as it was deliuered in one or moe SERMONS.</p>
            <p>By IOHN TRASKE, Preacher of Gods Word ſometimes at <hi>Axmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> in <hi>Deuon:</hi> afterwards at the <hi>Fleete</hi> in <hi>London:</hi> and now at <hi>Tillingham</hi> in <hi>Dengie</hi> hundred in ESSEX.</p>
            <q>I ſaid, I will not make mention of him, nor ſpeake any more in his Name: But his word was in my heart, as a burning fire ſhut vp in my bones, and I was weary with forbearing, and I could not ſtay: For I heard the defaming of many. &amp;c. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſay they, and we will report it: all my familiars watched for my halting, <bibl>
                  <hi>Ier. 20.9.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T.S.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2804:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2804:2"/>
            <head>To the Beneuolent READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, I call thee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſing thou wilt reade. And I adde <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolent,</hi> to difference a holy Reader, from a prophane derider. I would be loath to proſtitute ſuch Pearls to ſwine. Publike &amp; powerfull Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the preualent meanes to prepare men for reading: and till that hath made way, reading is no more auaileable, then to the Eunuch, without <hi>Philips</hi> guide to the true ſence. Such Readers I call vpon to reade this tractate, that they
<pb facs="tcp:2804:3"/> may ſee the effects of Preaching, not onely in the generall ſeparation which it makes between Pagans and Chriſtians: but in that it deuides betweene Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and true worſhippers; and between ſuch as haue the forme, and ſuch as haue alſo the power of godlineſſe: yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſuch as haue the power onely in Seeking; and ſuch as Walke familiarly with God; and againe, betweene Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, in reſpect of the babiſh; or ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er eſtate; yea, of the Father-hood that is Chriſt Ieſus. And betweene theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and themſelues; betweene the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and fleſh; the ſeede of God, and of man; the right and contrary part; the new man and the old; the inward and outward man; the law of the minde, and of the members; Chriſt in vs, and Adam on vs; the regenerate, and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate part; yea, which is moſt of all, betweene the ſoule and ſpirit: If in theſe any light be yeelded, let God haue all
<pb facs="tcp:2804:3"/> the praiſe: and I wiſh thee this benefit, that it may diſcouer thine election, and make it ſure vnto thee; either by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thee to be at leaſt a ſeeker of Gods fauour, a labourer for reconciliation with God; one I meane in the throbs and throwes of the new birth in that firſt, generall, or vniuerſall Repentance that makes way to remiſsion, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares for admiſsion,<note place="margin">Mar. 1.4. Act. 2.37.38 Act. 26.18.</note> into the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by Faith in Chriſt Ieſus. If thou be ſo wounded, thou maiſt learne hence where to be healed. If thou be healed, and at liberty, it will warme, comfort, cleanſe, quicken, yea, renew thy ſtrength. If thou know all this already, I ſhall haue thy aſſent, if more, I expect thy beſt ayde, and humbly, and as hartily deſire thee to perfect ſo weake begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. It was at firſt prepared onely for one Congregation; if it become profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to more, it is that I deſire. And aboue all things, let vs now pray that
<pb facs="tcp:2804:4"/> the Goſpell ſo plentifully Preached, may haue theſe powerfull effects in theſe frozen, and benummed times. That <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> may be diſtinctly Preached, and <hi>Faith in Chriſt</hi> plainely vnfolded. Now is the time to be induſtrious, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, for vs of the Miniſtery; to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe whom Sathan hath ſcattered: and to comfort ſad hearts, and confirme weake hands againſt approaching try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als. Oh let vs redouble our paines in Preaching, Catechiſing, and eſpecially to put vp feruent praiers, with ſtrong cryes and teares, to him that is able to cauſe our peace to flouriſh, Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to ſpread abroad; Antichriſts to decay, and come to nought; to diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage Sathan; that ſo Gods people may be eſtabliſhed to ſtand faſt, fight valiantly, and be more then Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in the euill day. And for mee, the leaſt of all Gods Miniſters; I deſire your Prayers, that I may make full
<pb facs="tcp:2804:4"/> proofe of my Miniſtery, in redeeming the time I haue loſt by Sathans wiles. And ſo I reſt for this time and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>An vnfeigned well-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, to all that deſire ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the heart: IOHN TRASKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_powers">
            <pb facs="tcp:2804:5"/>
            <head>Powers of the Word Preached.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Conſidered either
<list>
                     <item>1 Generally, as
<list>
                           <item>1 Spreading.</item>
                           <item>2 Drawing.</item>
                           <item>3 Searching.</item>
                           <item>4 Diuiding.</item>
                           <item>5 Preuailing.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 More particularly, and that either,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>1 Common to
<list>
                     <item>Elect, and</item>
                     <item>Reprobate</item>
                  </list> as
<list>
                     <item>1 Conuincing.</item>
                     <item>2 Terrifying.</item>
                     <item>3 Humbling.</item>
                     <item>4 Reſtraining.</item>
                     <item>5 Reforming.</item>
                     <item>6 Aſtoniſhing.</item>
                     <item>7 Delighting.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 Peculiar to
<list>
                     <item>1 Reprobate which are
<list>
                           <item>1 Inſencible, as
<list>
                                 <item>1 Hardening.</item>
                                 <item>2 Deſtroying.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Sencible
<list>
                                 <item>1 Binding.</item>
                                 <item>2 Tormenting.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Elect, in
<list>
                           <item>1 Conuerting
<list>
                                 <item>1 Opening.</item>
                                 <item>2 Pricking.</item>
                                 <item>3 Bruiſing.</item>
                                 <item>4 Turning.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 Conſuming, as
<list>
                                 <item>1 Healing.</item>
                                 <item>2 Looſing.</item>
                                 <item>3 Heating.</item>
                                 <item>4 Comforting.</item>
                                 <item>5 Killing.</item>
                                 <item>6 Quickening.</item>
                                 <item>7 Renewing.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2804:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The power of Preaching,</hi> OR THE POWERFVLL Effects of the WORD truely Preached and rightly applyed, as it was deliuered in one or moe SERMONS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE 4.32.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For his word was with power.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the preparation to Chriſts Miniſtery; the execution thereof; and the confirmation of the truth taught, by Myracles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2804:6"/> done, whereſoeuer hee became.</p>
            <p>The preparation was by a fierce and violent temptation with which he was aſſaulted, as it may appeare to ſuch as read the Chapter to the 14 verſe: the execution of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery may be ſeene from thence to the 33. and the miracles hee did in the remainder of this Chapter, to the end thereof.</p>
            <p>Theſe words of the Euangeliſt which I haue read, doe concerne the execution of his glorious Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; in which conſider:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Country where he began to preach, <hi>Galile,</hi> his owne Country where hee had leaſt eſteeme, <hi>Verſe</hi> 14.24.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next, the places in that Country, the two chiefe Townes, <hi>Nazareth</hi> &amp; <hi>Capernaum,</hi> verſ. 16.31.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Alſo in thoſe Cities, what place he made choiſe of, not priuate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2804:6"/> houſes, as Conuenticlers, nor the ſtreetes, as fanaticall perſons are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, but the chiefe place of concourſe, to thoſe excellent ends, the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> Verſe 16.28.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Adde hereunto, the <hi>Time</hi> when: euen that ſet time which the Law enioyned, on which the people vſually met, on the <hi>Sabbaoth dayes,</hi> hee moſt vſually preached, <hi>Verſe</hi> 16.31.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Beſides theſe, wee haue the manner of his Preaching: <hi>He ſtood vp for to read, and hauing receiued the Booke, and read what hee would, he cloſed it, deliuered it to the Miniſter, and ſate downe and Preached,</hi> Verſe 16.17.20.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Moreouer, the matter of his Sermon was an explication of the Prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> with an appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the preſent times, <hi>Verſe</hi> 18.21.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2804:7"/>7. Laſtly, the effects that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon his Preaching, to take them in the ſame order (the Euangeliſt layes them downe) are theſe and ſuch like:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Divulgation.</hi> There went a fame of him throughout all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion round about, <hi>Verſe</hi> 14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Glorification.</hi> He was glorified of all, <hi>Verſe</hi> 15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Attention.</hi> The eyes of all were faſtened vpon him, <hi>Verſe</hi> 20.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Approbation.</hi> All bare him witneſſe that his words were grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>Verſe</hi> 22.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Admiration.</hi> They all won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, at his ſo gracious words, <hi>Verſe</hi> 22.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Indignation.</hi> There were of the chiefe of them filled with wrath, and roſe vp and thruſt him out of the City, and bringing him to the brow of the hill whereon the City was
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2804:7"/> built, they would haue caſt him downe headlong, but that paſſing through the midſt of them, he went his way, <hi>Verſe</hi> 28.29.30.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Stupefaction.</hi> They were aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at his doctrine.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of all theſe is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the words which I haue cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for my Text;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For his Word was with power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if the Euangeliſt ſhould ſay in more words: you may thinke it ſtrange that Preaching ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch effects; but if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cauſe, you may be eaſily ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied: Seeing ſo great was the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene his Preaching and others of that time, that whereas they moued nothing at all, got no fame, wan no glory to their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, procured neither approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, admiration, nor ſo much as attention to the Word by their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2804:8"/> Preaching: ſeeing their Preaching was cold, without any life, as if one told a dreame: Hee became famous, glorious, and moſt admirable; hee ſpake with authority, &amp; his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was ſo liuely, and became ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall to all, in one kinde or other, that hee vexed the very ſoules of wicked men that heard him; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed all that attended his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For his Word was with power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words there may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Connexion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Propoſition.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Connexion in the <hi>Cauſall (For,)</hi> which ſheweth it to be the reaſon which the Euangeliſt giues of the manifold effects which Chriſts Preaching produced:</p>
            <p>The Propoſition it ſelfe is affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, in which may be conſidered,
<list>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2804:8"/>
                  <item>1. The Subiect: <hi>His Word.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The Predicate: <hi>was with power.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To ſet vpon the Connexion or the Cauſall, and to conſider theſe words with their relation to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of the Chapter: this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine will thence ariſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Where the word is powerfully Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, it is effectuall in one kinde or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſuch as doe heare it.</hi> or, <hi>The word powerfully Preached, is effectuall to the hearers in one kinde or other.</hi> This truth needes no other footing then this of our Euangeliſt: He tels vs that the true cauſe of the ſpreading of Chriſts fame, and the high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme hee procured in the hearts of ſome hearers, as alſo of the wrath and rage of others was this, he Preached with authoritie: <hi>His word was with power.</hi> So we may ſee alſo when the Lord Ieſus had ended
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2804:9"/> that Sermon on the Mount, the people were aſtoniſhed at his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.28.29.</note> 
               <hi>for his word was with power, and not as the Scribes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may be ſeene in the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of all the Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; to inſtance in a few of them: <hi>Eliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>a man ſubiect to the like paſſions as we are,</hi> what powerfull effects at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended his Preaching? Witneſſe his preuailing ſo farre to the conuiction of his hearers,<note place="margin">1 King. 19.40.</note> 
               <hi>as that they obeyed his word in the ſlaughter of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of Baal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 King.</note>And <hi>Elizeus</hi> or <hi>Eliſha</hi> became as it were guide of Kingdomes, by the power of this Word,<note place="margin">Ion. 3.</note> as his Hiſtory ſhewes: yea, <hi>Ionas</hi> himſelfe preuailed with great <hi>Niniueh,</hi> ſo farre as to bring the King, his Nobles, and all the City to true repentance.</p>
            <p>That Voyce of a Cryer in the Wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> drew all to his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2804:9"/> yea, conuicted Souldiers,<note place="margin">Luke 3.</note> Publicans, and People, in great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> drew three thouſand to the Church at one Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; and fiue thouſand at another;<note place="margin">Acts 1.41. &amp; 4.3.</note> and at another Sermon of his,<note place="margin">Acts 5.21.35.</note> the Senate were cut at the heart, by the power of his Word.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Paul</hi> ſubdued whole Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Faith,<note place="margin">Acts 13. &amp; 14, &amp;c.</note> by his powerfull Preaching; and conuinced Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers of all ſorts, to the enraging of ſome againſt his perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> The reaſon is, becauſe otherwiſe it could not appeare to be as it is, a powerfull Word;<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> it muſt loſe its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, and ceaſe to be a word of power:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.18.</note> whereas it is the power of God, to the ſaluation of the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and the condemnation of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Adde this alſo, that it ſhould elſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2804:10"/> returne in vaine, and void of the chiefe end for which it was ſent. Whereas we know, that as the raine commeth down, and the ſnow from Heauen, and returneth not thither, but watereth the earth, and maketh it bring forth and bud; that it may giue ſeed to the Sower, and bread to the Eater: ſo ſaith the Lord, <hi>ſhall my Word be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 55.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>that goeth forth out of my mouth, it ſhall not returne vnto mee void; but it ſhall accompliſh that which I pleaſe, and it ſhall proſper in the thing whereunto I ſent it.</hi> And the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> tels vs plainely in the perſon of all holy Miniſters:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>We are vnto God a ſweet ſauour in Chriſt, in them that are ſaued, and in them that periſh:</hi> to the one we are <hi>the ſauour of death vnto death;</hi> and to the other, <hi>the ſauour of life vnto life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> Beſides theſe, Antichriſts miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry produceth powerfull effects:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2804:10"/> therefore Chriſts Miniſtery muſt be farre more powerfu l,<note place="margin">2 Theſ 2.8.9.</note> and produce more manifeſt effects where it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> Laſtly, the maine or chiefe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of preaching, is to wreſtle and fight-with, yea, to ouercome all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as it is expreſſed in the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> that powerfull Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, where God ſaith to him: <hi>See,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſet thee ouer the Nations, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Kingdomes, to root out, and to pull downe, and to deſtroy, and throw downe, to build, and to plant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But ſome obiecting againſt this, may ſay: True it is, that all theſe may ſerue to proue that Preaching was powerfull in the dayes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, but what is that to our dayes? We may not looke for ſuch power in Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> And why not at this day, the like
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2804:11"/> power in Preaching?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 59.1.</note>Is Gods hand ſhortned? or his power weakened? Is not <hi>Ieſus Chriſt the ſame yeſterday,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>to day, and for euer?</hi> Hath hee not promiſed to be with his Seruants in preaching to the end of the World?<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20.</note> and that with the aſſiſtance of all power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and in Earth? Is not the Holy Ghoſt the power of God,<note place="margin">Luke 1.35.</note> in Chriſts Miniſters at this day? Doth not the Euangeliſt <hi>Iohn</hi> record a promiſe that is laſting,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.12.</note> where it is written; <hi>Whoſoeuer beleeueth on Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the workes that Chriſt did, ſhall ſuch a beleeuer doe: yea, greater workes then thoſe hee did in the dayes of his fleſh? Is there not as much neede of like power in the preaching of the Word now, as there was then? yea, and more, ſeeing wee haue no miracles to confirme the Word? Haue we not Diuels, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2804:11"/> damned Atheiſts to oppoſe, and contemne the Word at this day? Are there not ſuch of whom it may be ſaid, as of <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer; That they are <hi>full of all ſubtilty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>and all miſchiefe, children of the Diuell, enemies of all righteouſneſſe, which ceaſe not to peruert the right wayes of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not Miniſters at this day as Fathers to beget? Mothers to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile-with, and bring forth? Nurſes to nouriſh? Watchmen to warne? Souldiers to fight for? and Stewards to giue euery man his portion of meate in due ſeaſon? Yea, is not one Miniſter ſometimes a Father, a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a Nurſe, a Watchman, a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and a Steward at one and the ſame inſtant; and doth not all this require great power?</p>
            <p>Are there not blinde men at this day that want ſight? lame that want
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2804:12"/> ſtrength? Lepers that need clenſing? ſicke that want health? ſtrayers that muſt be ſought out? ſuch as are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, to be raiſed up? dumbe, deafe, and dead men, to be made to ſpeak, heare, and come out of their graues? And doe not ſuch workes require great power? If it were but to make a man that is dumbe, deafe, and blinde, to vnderſtand, it were a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great difficulty, and requires great power; but to raiſe vp a dead man, that hath long ſlept the ſleepe of death, will any cold dreamer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake ſuch a ſleeper? No verily: It muſt be ſuch whoſe Miniſtery is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with power.</p>
            <p>And that there is required won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull power at this day, conſider further, that wee haue not onely dead men to raiſe, blinde men to make to ſee, wounded to heale, ſicke to recouer, impriſoned to ſet free,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2804:12"/> ſtrayers to ſeeke out, lambes to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſheepe to feede, babes to whom wee giue milke, and ſtronger to whom ſtrong meate is belonging: but we haue Sorcerers to withſtand, Beares and Lyons to combate with; Philiſtines to whom wee muſt goe, ſonnes of <hi>Anake</hi> to conquer: yea, moreouer wee may haue <hi>Ahabs</hi> to ſpeake vnto: <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> to reſiſt: <hi>Hamans</hi> to contend with: <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> to reproue. We may haue <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> to march after vs: <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> to diſgrace vs publikely: <hi>Sanballats</hi> to oppoſe, and mocke vs: <hi>Iudaſſes</hi> to betray vs: <hi>Demaſſes</hi> to forſake vs: <hi>Halting</hi> people to comber vs: <hi>Alexanders</hi> to withſtand our words: <hi>Corahs</hi> to raiſe forces againſt vs: <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes</hi> to entrap vs: <hi>High Prieſts</hi> to ſcorne vs: <hi>Pilates</hi> to condemne vs: <hi>Multitudes</hi> to ſlander vs, and the truth we teach: And if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2804:13"/> it ſhould ſo come to paſſe, as it hath befallen our<note n="*" place="margin">Wicliffe. Huſſe. Luther.</note> brethren, is not here ſtill a worke of great power? ſhould we ſhrinke in ſuch ſtraights? Adde hereunto that the Word is the ſame for euer: yea, the words of God are as nayles,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.11.</note> which being well driuen, doe hold with power; as goades to prouoke and ſtirre vp:<note place="margin">Hoſea 6.5.</note> axes to hew and ſquare; as fire to burne and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:<note place="margin">Ier. 23.29.</note> as an hammer to breake the rockes; as arrowes that wound; a ſword that diuides:<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.5.</note> yea, a ſharpe ſword with two edges,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> to diuide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſoule and the ſpirit, the ioynts and the marrow: And ſo the Word is at this day, quicke and powerfull.</p>
            <p>So that you now ſee that obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on anſwered: namely, it is affirmed; That Preaching is alwayes power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whether wee reſpect Gods power, vnchangeable: Chriſts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2804:13"/> promiſe, of the aſſiſtance of all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in heauen and in earth; the powerfull worke of the Miniſtery, in reſpect of their charge, of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the word it ſelfe, that cannot be abated: yea, that by how much the elder the world waxeth, and the riper in ſinne, and by how much the more all miracles are granted to be now ceaſed, by ſo much the more power muſt of neceſſity ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing Gods power is manifeſt in the greateſt weakeneſſe:</hi> And where ſinne moſt abounds, Gods grace in powerfull Preaching, aboundeth much more in ſuch as are called.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Now ſome may demand what are the effects of powerfull Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and how may they be diſcerned?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> For anſwere hereunto: know, that the powerfull effects of Preaching are manifold: and they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered,
<list>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2804:14"/>
                  <item>1. Either Generally:</item>
                  <item>2. Or Particularly.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>If wee conſider them Generally, they may be theſe, or ſuch like:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
               </note>1. Firſt, a growing or <hi>ſpreading</hi> power: as may appeare by ſome ſimilitudes to which it is compared, as that of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.23.</note> where he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it by a tender <hi>twig,</hi> cut off from the high Cedar, and planted on an high and eminent mountaine, which bringeth forth boughes, and beares fruit, and becomes a goodly Cedar, that vnder it may dwell all fowle of euery wing, euen in the ſhadow of it.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.30 31.</note> Or that where the Lord Ieſus compares it to a <hi>graine of Muſtard-ſeede,</hi> which is the leaſt of all ſeeds, and yet being ſowen, groweth vp, and becommeth a tree.<note place="margin">Act. 19.10.</note> And it is expreſly ſaid of the Word, that it grew powerfully in the Apoſtles dayes:<note place="margin">Verſe 14.</note> So in this Chapter, the ſame
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2804:14"/> of Chriſts Preaching was ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, throughout all the Region round about.<note place="margin">Col. 1.6.</note> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs, that it was in his time ſpread ouer all the world, and ſo you haue the growing, increaſing, or ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding power of the word.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </note> the word powerfully Preached hath a <hi>drawing</hi> power. And it may be well ſaid of power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Preachers, they draw more after them with their tongues, then <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> could driue before him with his club: It will draw all men to it, we may ſee it, in the power and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſts word:<note place="margin">Mat. 3.5.7.</note> who knew nothing, but the Doctrine, and Baptiſme of Repentance: Yet all the Regions flocked after him, and came to his Preaching. And when his Diſciples told him that all men came to Chriſt, as they had formerly to him: he anſwereth, <hi>that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2804:15"/> a man can receiue nothing except it be giuen him from aboue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.26.</note> As if he ſhould haue ſaid: Chriſt hath this power of drawing men after him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.32.</note> from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue: and ſaith further, that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Chriſt in that thing muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and his power decreaſe: and addeth yet further, that therein is his ioy fulfilled.<note place="margin">Verſe 42.</note> And in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is this confirmed by that, when Chriſt went into a deſart place, all the people were drawne thither al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: yea, his word was ſo powerfull, that it drew them by multitudes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.14 22.24.25.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Sea, vnto him: ſo that they would haue made him a King, for the word hath a drawing power.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 <hi>Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </note>Thirdly, the Word powerfully preached, hath a <hi>ſearching</hi> power: it can enter into the diſcerning of the inward parts.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.13.</note> It diſcerneth the ſecret thoughts, and intents of the heart; <hi>All things are open and naked
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2804:15"/> to the eyes of it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.25.</note> It findes out mens purpoſes, layes open their moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret intents, yea, reueales the very depths of Sathan: It can goe into heauen, and ſhew vs what treaſures are therein ſtore, it can dig into hell, and diſcouer the torments, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for impenitent and rebellious perſons; and ſo you haue the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Deuiding</hi>
               </note> it hath a <hi>deuiding</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: by which it ſeuers one thing from another. It pierceth euen to the deuiding aſunder of the ſoule,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> and the ſpirit, and the ioynts, and the marrow. See this alſo where the Lord ſaith in this regard: I am not come to ſend peace but a ſword.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.34 35.</note> I am come to deuide betweene the Father, and the Sonne, the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Mother: the Daughter in law, and the Mother in law. As it is expreſſed in ſo many words, by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2804:16"/> another Euangeliſt thus. Suppoſe yee that I am come to ſend peace on the earth. I tell you nay, but rather deuiſion:<note place="margin">Luke 12.35</note> for from henceforth there ſhall be fiue, in one houſe, deuided, three againſt two, and two againſt three. The Father ſhall be deuided againſt the Sonne, and the Sonne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Father, the Mother againſt the Daughter, and the Daughter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Mother, the Mother in law, againſt her Daughter in law, and the Daughter in law againſt her Mother in law. Yea, this word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides between cleane and vncleane; holy and prophane; ſuch as ſweare, and ſuch as feare an oath; betweene righteouſneſſe, and vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; light, and darkeneſſe: true worſhip and Idolatry; betweene Chriſt and Antichriſt. So that the word hath a deuiding power.</p>
            <p>To theſe may be added, the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2804:16"/> power of the word,<note place="margin">5 <hi>Preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi>
               </note> in that it beareth downe all oppoſition. It will roote out, and throw downe; deſtroy and conſume: it will build, and plant. It will caſt out foule ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and conuict Coniurers, and make them bring forth their Bookes of curious arts, and burne them euen to the value of many thouſand pieces of ſiluer.<note place="margin">Act. 19.19.20.</note> So mightily will it grow, and preuaile where it is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> By theſe then, before we goe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen by theſe generall powers or effects of the word, may Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters examine the truth of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery; euen at this day: Doth the word in thy mouth ſpreade it ſelfe into all the borders of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? doth it enforce people, at leaſt to talke of thee by the walles? doth it draw them to Church, and gaine attention from them? Doſt thou
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2804:17"/> perceiue that it ſearcheth their hearts, and layeth open their ſecret practiſes, or doth it ſet them at ods, and make a ſeparation between the godly, and vngodly; the righteous, and the wicked; the religious, and prophane? and doth it preuaile mightily, in the reſtraining of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, and reforming the diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Doſt thou finde all theſe, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe? then maiſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with comfort, that Gods po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer doth attend thy preaching: and ſuch people as ſee theſe effects, may ſay that God is preſent in ſuch Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, of a truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> By this ſuch are iuſtly reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as doe ſtumble at theſe, and ſuch like of all other Preaching, they like that worſt, which ſpreads it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; drawes people after it, gaines attention, ſearcheth out the very ſecret thoughts of the heart, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2804:17"/> makes a ſeparation where it comes; preuailing mightily in the conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of ſome, the conuerting of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the comforting of the godly, the diſcouery of the hypocrite, and prophane perſon. They cry downe ſuch Preachers, and ſet themſelues againſt ſuch Preaching with all their power: but this will appeare more plainely, when we come to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular powers of the Word.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> Let this then ſtirre vp all Gods people to thankfulneſſe, where ſuch a powerfull Miniſtery is enioyed. Doe you perceiue that your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſame is ſpread farre and neere? doe the people of his Pariſh come to him, and flocke to his Miniſtery? Doe you find that his word comes home, and entreth into your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, diueth into your hearts and conſciences, diſcouereth all your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret practiſes, and preuaileth more
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2804:18"/> and more in theſe things? breake forth into the praiſes of God, and returne due thankes to his Maieſty, for his great mercy, in affording ſuch a Miniſtery, as hath ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects: Such a Miniſtery is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly of God. <hi>For Chriſts Word is with power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To come more particularly to ſhew the powers of the Word; we may conſider it, as it is common both to the Elect and reprobate, and as it may be peculiar to either of them.</p>
            <p>The common powers which worke both in the Elect, and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</hi>
               </note>Firſt, a conuincing power; when men are not onely made to ſee a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene truth and errour: but alſo conuicted in their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that truth is truth, and error is error. This power in preaching,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2804:18"/> hath footing on a direct promiſe, to all ſuch as preach by the holy Spirit.<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.8.</note> They ſhall conuince the World of ſinne, of righteouſneſſe, and of iudgement.<note place="margin">Acts 18.28</note> So <hi>Apollos</hi> a man mighty in the holy Scriptures, did powerfully preuaile to the conuicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the gaine-ſaying Iewes; and that publikely ſhewing them that Ieſus was Chriſt. So it is written;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.24.</note> That if all Propheſie, that is, ſpeake the Word plainely with power: If an vnlearned man, or an vnbeleeuer be preſent, he is conuinced by ſuch powerfull preaching.</p>
            <p>Secondly, powerfull preaching,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </note> hath a terrifying power. As when <hi>Herod</hi> heard onely of the birth of Chriſt, he was terrified,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.1.2.</note> and all <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> with him.<note place="margin">Acts 24.25</note> And wicked <hi>Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> hearing a powerfull Preacher onely reaſon in his preſence of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, temperance, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2804:19"/> to come; he trembled. And to ſuch hath God reſpect,<note place="margin">Iſai 66.1.</note> eſpecially as tremble at his Word: ſo that the word powerfully preached, workes trembling in both Elect, and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.<note place="margin">Hab. 3.16.</note> For ſo <hi>Habacuck</hi> ſaith; I heard, and my belly trembled, my lippes quiuered at the voyce, and yet hee was an holy Prophet: and <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelfe at the promulgation of the Law,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.21.</note> was conſtrained to ſay; <hi>I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly feare, and quake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</hi>
               </note>Thirdly, the Word powerfully preached, hath an humbling power, both in elect and reprobate: as wee perceiue in that place before allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, for the conuicting power, that ſuch vnlearned and vnbeleeuing as heare ſuch preaching, fall downe on their faces, and worſhip God, and acknowledge that God is preſent in ſuch Preachers of a truth. And ſuch power was in Chriſts preaching in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2804:19"/> dayes of his fleſh,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.29. Mat. 1.24.</note> that it humbled many, euen Diuels, and wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as well as others: that they came running, and kneeling downe,<note place="margin">Mar. 10.17.18.</note> yea, falling downe and confeſſing, that he was the Sonne of God, and a good man.<note place="margin">1 King. 21.24.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab</hi> alſo humbled himſelfe for a little ſeaſon: And <hi>Cain</hi> was humbled by the power of this word, though <hi>Ahab</hi> too little,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.14.</note> and <hi>Caine</hi> ouer-much.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Reſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
               </note> the word powerfully Preached, hath a <hi>reſtrayning</hi> power. It keepes the reprobate as the elect from breaking out into foule enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, &amp; doth reſtrayne them from groſſe ſinnes, as in the preſence of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 32.1.2.3</note> the people were reſtrayned from Idolatrie: which in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, they committed with an high hand. And wee reade of a King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> euen <hi>Ioaſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 24.2.</note> whole heart was not right, yet did hee that which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2804:20"/> was right in Gods fight, all the daies of <hi>Iehoiada</hi> the Prieſt. And experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth teach vs, that where the word is moſt zealouſly preſſed, and powerfully vrged, ſuch places are farre more free from open impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, then other places where it is not ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi> Ioh. 6.66.</note>Furthermore, the word hath a <hi>reforming</hi> power; in both elect, and reprobates. As may appeare in thoſe beleeuers, that went backe from Chriſt: and eſpecially of <hi>Herod,</hi> that wicked man, of whom we read, that he feared <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt,<note place="margin">Mar. 6.20.</note> knowing that he was a iuſt, and an holy man, and obſerued him, and when hee heard, hee did many things, and heard him gladly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6 <hi>Aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing.</hi>
               </note>Adde to theſe, that the word hath an <hi>aſtoniſhing</hi> power: by which it ſtupifies, and doth amaze, as well the reprobate, as the elect: as wee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2804:20"/> ſee in <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 13.8.</note> of whom wee reade that hee beleeued, and when he was baptized, continued with <hi>Philip,</hi> and wondered. And we reade alſo of the Preaching of Chriſt, that the hearers were aſtoniſhed at his doctrine,<note place="margin">Mark. 2.21 22.</note> for hee taught as one that had power, and not as the Scribes.</p>
            <p>Alſo the word powerfully Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, is <hi>delightfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 <hi>Delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </note> as well to the wicked, as the godly: that it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull to the godly, is without queſtion, it is the very ioy and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of their hearts:<note place="margin">Ier. 15.16. Pſal. 19.10. Ezech. 33.32.</note> ſweeter to them then hony, and the hony-combe; but to the very wicked, <hi>Ezechiel</hi> tels vs, that ſuch whoſe hearts doe ſtill goe after their couetouſneſſe, yet his word was as pleaſant to them as a louely ſong, of one that hath a pleaſant voyce, and can play well on an inſtrument.<note place="margin">Mar. 6.20.</note> And of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> wee reade that hee heard <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2804:21"/> gladly:<note place="margin">Mat. 13.10.21.</note> Alſo we ſee it in that Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the ſtony ground; the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation whereof is to reprobate hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, that yet receiue the word with ioy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> By theſe common powers of the word, we may perceiue how farre reprobates may goe in hearing, and what effects it worketh, euen in the damned, as in the ſaued: they may be conuicted, terrified, humbled in ſome meaſure, reſtrained, reformed, and delighted by the power of the word: ſo that ſuch as can goe no further, haue not ſet one foote in conuerſion beyond a very repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: How manifeſtly wretched then are all ſuch as neuer yet felt theſe powers in themſelues, but that theſe may alſo be ſeene, let vs come to the peculiar powers of the word, in elect and reprobate.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the powers of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2804:21"/> word Preached in the reprobate hearer, and they are either ſencible,<note place="margin">Inſencible</note> or inſencible:</p>
            <p>The inſencible powers of the word Preached, in reprobates, is:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Hardning</hi>
               </note> that <hi>hardening</hi> power of the word, whereby their hearts are hardened, and their very conſciences ſeared,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.2.</note> as with an hot Iron: that whereas they had at firſt hearing, ſome ſence, they become by often conuiction, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſenceleſſe: Of this power,<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.9.10.</note> God ſpeaketh to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> whoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſeemeth to be chiefly to that end, as it appeareth where we reade it written, that God ſaith vnto him, <hi>goe tell this people,</hi> heare yee indeed, but vnderſtand not: and ſee yee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but perceiue not? Make the heart of this people fat; and make their eares heauy, and ſhut their eyes. This the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth to the vnbeleeuing Iewes,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2804:22"/> where he ſaith; Well ſpake the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Act. 28.25:26.27.</note> by <hi>Eſayas</hi> the Prophet, vnto our Fathers, ſaying, Goe vnto this people and ſay; hearing you ſhall heare, and ſhall not vnderſtand; and ſeeing, you ſhall ſee; and ſhall not perceiue: For the heart of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is waxed groſſe.<note place="margin">Eph. 4.19.</note> And the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs of ſome that are paſt fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </note>Another power of the word, which is alſo inſencible, may be that <hi>deſtroying</hi> power: whereby the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are not onely more and more hardened, but haue all the faculties of the ſoule peruerted, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees deſtroyed.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.16</note> And that the word hath ſuch a deſtroying power, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth where it is called, the ſauour of death vnto death.<note place="margin">Ier. 1.10.</note> And <hi>Ieremies</hi> miſſion gaue him power to deſtroy and throw downe, as well as to build and plant. And the Apoſtle
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2804:22"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> tels the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.8 &amp; 13.10.</note> or the elect at <hi>Corinth,</hi> that hee vſed his power toward them to edification, and not to deſtruction: ſo that the word Preached, hath a deſtroying power.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſencible</hi> powers of the word,<note place="margin">Sencible.</note> in the very reprobate are either that tormenting power, or elſe that bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power.</p>
            <p>And that ſuch a <hi>ſcorching</hi> or tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Scorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </note> or cutting power of the word, is ſencibly apprehended by reprobates, we may perceiue in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab,</hi> who in that reſpect,<note place="margin">1 King. 18.17. &amp; 21.20. &amp; 22.8.</note> called <hi>Eliah</hi> the troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and hated <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caiah,</hi> another powerfull Preacher, for that hee vexed or tormented him, neuer Preaching good vnto him, but euill. And in <hi>Foelix,</hi> who was ſo vexed by <hi>Pauls</hi> reaſoning,<note place="margin">Act. 24.25.</note> that hee ſent him away And the Iewes who being conuicted,<note place="margin">Act. 7.54.57.</note> were cut at the heart by the Preaching
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2804:23"/> of <hi>Steuen,</hi> and gnaſhed vpon him with their teeth: and ſtopping their eares, ranne vpon him, as they did on his Maſter, as hath beene ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of this Chapter:<note place="margin">Verſe 28.29.</note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is compared to fire which ſcorcheth men with great heate, and cauſeth them to diſcouer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by blaſphemies.<note place="margin">Reu. 16.8.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Binding.</hi>
               </note>Another ſencible power of the Word, is that <hi>binding</hi> power, by which wicked reprobates doe ſee themſelues bound hand and foote,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.13.</note> and caſt out of the Church, and Gods protection; that is, doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that they are ſeuered from the godly, and ſhut out of the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in light: and doe alſo perceiue that they haue no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer any more to moue a foote to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that way, or an hand to that excellent worke. And this is done by the power of the holy ſpirit in<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.23.</note>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2804:23"/> the word Preached.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> By this we learne, not to thinke it ſtrange though ſome hearers waxe worſe &amp; worſe, &amp; become more hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, and leſſe ſencible, either of mercies or iudgements, euen where the word is powerfully Preached;<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.8.</note> yea, become not onely benummed, that they euen fall aſleepe ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the Preaching of the ſame; but alſo (to ſuch as vnderſtand) become apparantly more ignorant and ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, more peruerſe, and peeuiſh: yea, are euen conſumed as it were to nothing by the Preaching thereof; that whereas they haue ſeemed to be pleaſed with a Sermon, and haue done ſome things gladly, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne other things which the word forbids: yea, beene much humbled with a kinde of trembling, and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment at the conuiction of their conſciences, now they are not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2804:24"/> ſtirred at all, nor delighted, nor yet at all doe admire it, but count it as a common thing, and by how much the more powerfull it is, by ſo much leſſe doe they regard it: yea, by ſo much more neglect it, &amp; contemne it. Nor yet may wee wonder that they are filled with wrath, and rage at the Preachers of it: ſeeing they doe plainely ſee themſelues ſencibly bound, as it were hand and foote, and caſt out amongſt dogges, and ſwine: and alſo continually ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and vexed by the heate, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uency of ſuch powerfull preaching. No wonder then if they cry downe ſuch Preaching, and get to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues heapes of teachers,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.4.</note> that if one pricke, another may pleaſe: You haue ſeene clearely, ſuch are the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of the word truely taught, that it tormenteth, bindeth, hardneth; yea, deſtroyeth and conſumeth the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2804:24"/> very reprobates: and there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther effect to be looked for in any ſuch, but theſe, to be trembled at in the naming of them.</p>
            <p>Come wee now to the powers of the word Preached, in the very E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, thoſe that are peculiar to them in a ſpeciall manner; and let vs take them either as they are manifeſted in their conuerſion, or confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And firſt in their <hi>conuerting:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</note> and they are either that opening, prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, bruſing, or that turning power of the word: and firſt of that ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning power.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Opening.</hi>
               </note> the word hath an <hi>opening</hi> power, whereby it doth not onely open the eyes of the Elect, as it may of the reprobate,<note place="margin">Numb. 24.16.</note> as <hi>Balaams</hi> eyes were opened: but in a more cleare manner,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.18.</note> are they made to ſee the myſteries of godlineſſe, then any
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2804:25"/> reprobate, and to this end their hearts are opened with <hi>Lidia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note> that they not onely vnderſtand, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect what they vnderſtand: and in this ſence it may be called the <hi>key</hi> of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 3.7.</note> that openeth, and no man ſhutteth: that is, that ſo openeth that it can neuer be ſhut or cloſed any more;<note place="margin">Mat. 13.11.</note> and this is proper to the Elect.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pricking.</hi>
               </note>Secondly, the word Preached, hath a <hi>pricking</hi> power: by which it doth not onely ſomewhat trouble, but throughly wound the very heart of Gods people,<note place="margin">Act. 1.37.</note> as were thoſe Conuerts to whom <hi>Peter</hi> Preached, they were pricked in their hearts: therefore is it in this reſpect, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red euen to ſharpe arrowes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.5.</note> as hath beene ſhewed; it pierceth into the very ſoules of poore ſinners, and makes them ſencible of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> and this is alſo proper
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2804:25"/> to the Elect.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Bruiſing.</hi>
               </note> the Word powerfully preached, hath the power of brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, yea, of breaking to pieces the very Elect, as <hi>Ieremiah</hi> tels vs,<note place="margin">Ier. 23.29.</note> where hee compares it to an hammer, that breaketh rockes. So it breaketh their hard and ſtony hearts, and maketh them not onely ſeeme nothing in their owne eyes, but alſo maketh them the more capable of the new worke of regeneration,<note place="margin">Ezech. 11.19.</note> as <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſpeakes, where God ſaith by him; I will take out your ſtony hearts, and giue you hearts of fleſh.</p>
            <p>This is that renting of the heart, which God requireth:<note place="margin">Ioel 2.13.</note> and that bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart, that he will not deſpiſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Word preached,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Turning.</hi>
               </note> hath alſo a turning power, by which it changeth mens mindes, and alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth their affections. So it was ſaid of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, that hee ſhould
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2804:26"/> goe before Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luke 1.17.</note> in the Spirit, and power of <hi>Elias,</hi> to turne the hearts of the Fathers to the Children, and the diſobedient to the wiſdome of the iuſt.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.1</note> So we reade, that it is one property of the Doctrine of God, to conuert the ſoule. And this power, the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> where he ſaith;<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.5.9.</note> Our Goſpell came not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in word onely, but alſo in power: in that it turned them from Idols to ſerue the liuing and true God. And this was the end of his ſending,<note place="margin">Acts 26.18</note> not onely to open mens eyes, but to turne them from darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to light, from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than to God: And ſo you haue the opening, pricking, bruiſing, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning power of the Word, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to the conuerting of the Elect, and ſo may be ſaid to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to them onely.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:2804:26"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> If this be ſo, that ſuch powers of the Word are in the Elect onely, then hereby ſuch as are deſirous to know their election to be of God, may try themſelues by theſe: Hath the Word preached opened thine eyes? yea, thine heart? and haſt thou felt a pricking power in thy ſoule, for ſinne? hath thine heart been, not onely pricked, but bruiſed? yea, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo, that thou art come to a ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniall? yea, to find thy ſelfe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? and art thou turned, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together changed, by the power of Preaching? Canſt thou truly ſay; thou ſeeſt, and vnderſtandeſt the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of thy ſinfull nature? and art grieued at the heart for ſinne? and doeſt finde, that by ſinne thou art euen become of no account, and that deſeruedly with God? and doſt thou finde thy heart quite turned, by a deteſtation of thy former euill
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2804:27"/> way, and a vehement care of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere to God, and being recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to his Maieſty? by theſe thou mayeſt bee able to conclude with comfort, that thou art in the true way to eternall life, and without doubt ordained to euerlaſting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. And that thou mayeſt be yet further aſſured, we will proceede to the power of the Word, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming ſuch as are thus turned to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming power.</note>The ſame Word that thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteth, doth alſo confirme the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted; and that by theſe powerfull effects which follow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Healing.</hi>
               </note>Firſt, the Word as it woundeth, ſo it healeth; it hath an healing power,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.20.</note> as the Pſalmiſt witneſſeth, where we reade of ſuch as are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſicke with the conſcience of ſinne; God ſent his Word, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2804:27"/> them. And Chriſt proclaimeth it in this Chapter, that his Word hath an healing power; where ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Propheſie of <hi>Eſayas</hi> to himſelfe, he ſaith;<note place="margin">Ver. 18.23.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa 61.6.</note> He is ſent to heale the broken in heart: which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet calles binde vp. So that the Word powerfully preached, is that good Samaritan,<note place="margin">Luke 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 30.</note> which bindes vp the wounds of that ſin-wounded Traueller; and the onely Balme of <hi>Gilead,</hi> that healing medicine, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by health is reſtored to the ſicke ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Let Gods people learne hence, where to haue recourſe for health: The Word is onely able to wound and heale; here are the leaues of that Tree to be gathered, which ſerue for the healing of the Nations.<note place="margin">Reu. 12.2.</note> If any be then wounded by the Word, let not that driue them from it, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther draw them to it; if euer they
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2804:28"/> will haue health, here, and no where elſe may they expect it; and it may be an argument of the truth of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, if the Word haue healed, as well as wounded thee: or if at leaſt thou ſeeke health at the Word preached.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Looſing.</hi>
               </note>Secondly, the Word hath alſo the power of loſing, or ſetting free, ſuch as are turned to God; that whereas before they haue liued in thraldome and bondage, now are they parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the glorious liberty of the ſonnes of God:<note place="margin">Luke 13.12.16.</note> yea, neuer did Chriſts word more manifeſtly free that daughter of <hi>Abraham,</hi> (whom Satan had bound eighteene yeeres, that ſhee could not lift vp her ſelfe) from that diuelliſh bond; then ſuch as are Gods, are free, and ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the word preached, to runne the wayes of Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.<note place="margin">Iſa 61.1.</note> Wee may ſee it in that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2804:28"/> of <hi>Eſayas,</hi> which our Sauiour applyeth to this end,<note place="margin">Verſe 18.</note> in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; where we reade, that he is ſent to preach deliuerance to the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, and to ſet at liberty ſuch as are bruiſed: yea, to preach the yeere of Iubilee,<note place="margin">Verſe 19.</note> or the acceptable yeere of the Lord. So is this power promiſed to all faithfull Preachers, in theſe words;<note place="margin">Mat. 16.19 &amp; 18.18.</note> Whatſoeuer you looſe on earth, ſhal be looſed in heauen: And whoſoeuers ſinnes you remit,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.23.</note> they are remitted. Th s our Lord alſo at another time affirmed, where hee ſaith; If you continue in my Word, then are you my Diſciples indeed:<note place="margin">Ioh 8.31.32.</note> and you ſhall know the truth, and the truth ſhall make you free.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> By this all may be able further to bee confirmed in the truth of their election; if they hauing beene by Nature ſinnes vaſſals,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.33.34.</note> and in bondage thereunto, led captiue by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2804:29"/> the Diuell at his owne will, and by the vertue and powerfull efficacy of the Word, are now loſed, and ſet at liberty, not onely to ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, but to walke, and to run the wayes of Gods Commandements. Try thy ſelfe then,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.17.</note> art thou ſuch a free man? Where the Spirit is, there is this liberty, ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul.</hi> Art thou then ſet at liberty? by what publike Sermon, or Sermons? or by what priuate application of the promiſes to thy ſoule? when, or ſince what time haſt thou perceiued the ſtriking off of thy chaines, the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the priſon doore, and yron gate of thy ſinnes, that thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt be admitted to the fellowſhip of the Saints? The Word powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached, doth heale, as well as wound; and looſe the Elect, as binde the reprobate. And ſo much alſo for the power of looſing, which is alſo
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2804:29"/> proper to Gods choſen people.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Heating.</hi>
               </note> the word powerfully Preached doth warme, yea, heate the cold hearts of poore humbled ſinners, and in this ſence it is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to fire, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.3.</note> where hee ſaith, His heart was hot within him, and while hee was mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing how to be ſilent (in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the wicked) the fire bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.<note place="margin">Ier. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.9.</note> And <hi>Ieremy</hi> reſoluing alſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſilence, tels vs that this word was in his heart as a burning fire, ſhut vp in his bones: inſomuch that he was weary with forbearing, and could not ſtay: And the Diſciples that had Chriſts company in their way to <hi>Emaus,</hi> ſay of his conference: Did not our hearts burne within vs while he talked with vs by the way?<note place="margin">Luke 24.32.</note> and this is that which the ſpirit findeth abſent in that Church of <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.15.19</note> Where it wiſheth that they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2804:30"/> were either hot or cold: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to be zealous, that is, to be hot and feruent.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> By this alſo may wee be further confirmed in the truth of our Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; if the word hath warmed, or doth heate vs:<note place="margin">Eph. 2.1.</note> We are cold all by nature, as being dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes: and ſo benummed with cold, and euen frozen in the dirt of wickedneſſe, if this word haue thawed vs, and ſo alſo warmed our hearts, and doth ſtill heate vs, that we can feelingly ſay, we are heated; yea, our hearts burne within vs, in prayer, holy conference, and in the Preaching of the word: and that the heate of it is ſo great, that it euen waſteth vs in the loue of God, zeale for his glory, and the loue of Gods Church, and of all men; yea, ſo great is this heate, that the many waters of diſcouragements,<note place="margin">Cant. 8.6.7</note> nor
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2804:30"/> flouds of oppoſition; yea, our owne raſh reſolutions cannot quench it. but it flaſheth out now and then, and will not be extinguiſhed: this is a notable confirmation of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of our eſtate, and that wee are vndoubtedly Gods Elect and choſen ones, ſeeing this is a power peculiar and properly belonging vnto them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi>
               </note> the word powerfully Preached, hath a <hi>comforting</hi> power, in Gods Elect. It is their comforter in all their troubles: this is that which wipeth all teares from their eyes: and by which they are dandled vpon the knees of Gods loue.<note place="margin">Iſai. 66.11.12. Pſal. 19.8.</note> So wee reade, that the Statutes of the Lord are right, reioycing the heart; yea, this word to <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15.16. Pſal. 119.14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</note> was his onely ioy. It was <hi>Dauids</hi> comfort in affliction: yea, hee reioyced as much in Gods word, as in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2804:31"/> of riches: It was ſweeter to his mouth then hony, and the hony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> This comfort of the word may be alſo a notable meanes of confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuch as are turned to God. Let mee ſay vnto ſuch, what is it that delights you? Is it the free pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpell? doth the word not onely ioy you in the hearing, and in time of proſperitie? but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cheare you in ſuffering, and in the greateſt trouble and aduerſity? Is it the word which as a Mother doth dandle thee, as a childe on the knees of ſound comfort, and wipe away all teares from thine eyes? be aſſured that thou art alſo one of Gods Elect, a redeemed one: If his powerfull word that hath made thee truely ſorrowfull, doth alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore ſound comforts vnto thee.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe, the powerfull word
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2804:31"/> doth alſo diſcouer its power in Gods Elect by <hi>killing</hi> them;<note place="margin">5 <hi>Killing.</hi>
               </note> yea, ſtriking them vnder the fifth rib of their ſinnes. The word will ſtrike the man of ſinne through the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſmote <hi>Goliah</hi> with a ſtone from his ſling: yea, it will make ſinne fall groueling to the earth, and cut off the very head of it. It will cut it at the heart, and naile it to the very Croſſe of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> as it is written; They that are Chriſts, haue crucified the fleſh with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and luſts.<note place="margin">Col. 3.3.4.</note> It mortifies ſuch as are Gods Elect in that manner, that they can ſay, They are dead,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.19.20</note> and, I liue no more. They that were dead in ſinne, are dead to ſinne by the power of this word where it is effectually Preached to the Elect.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Try wee our ſelues alſo by this, doe we finde the word ſo powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preuailing, that it hath ſlaine vs,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2804:32"/> and crucified our fleſh with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and luſts?<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.8.</note> hath it deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſtrong holds of ſinne, and all the workes of the Diuell in vs? hath it bound the ſtrong man and caſt him out? and doth it daily, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery time wee heare,<note place="margin">Luke 11.</note> mortifie the deedes of the fleſh, our earthly members?<note place="margin">Col. 3.4.</note> by this we may alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it is profitable to vs; and that we are Gods Elect, by this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer which is peculiar to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6 <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
               </note>Adde to theſe, that <hi>quickning</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the word Preached, whereby it doth reuiue, and put not onely heate,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.24.25.</note> but life into ſuch as heare it. Of this ſpeaketh the Lord of life, where he ſaith;<note place="margin">Iſai. 55.3.</note> The dead ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God, and ſuch as heare ſhall liue. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſayas,</hi> Heare, and your ſoules ſhall liue. And how were the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2804:32"/> 
               <hi>Epheſians</hi> quickened?<note place="margin">Eph. 2.1. &amp; 1.13.</note> who before were dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes: but by the Preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, this powerfull word?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> How farre off then are ſuch from any aſſurance of their election to be of God, who know not what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to this life? They are ſencible of the life of the body, but this life, it is to them a ſtrange thing, this word, <hi>The iuſt ſhall liue by faith;</hi> is a Myſtery of Myſteries, a darke and obſcure riddle: and therefore it may much confirme, and adde to the comfort of Gods people, when they can truely ſay, that they now liue; it is by the faith of the Sonne of God, who loued them, and gaue himſelfe for them. Art thou now quickned? ſince when haſt thou felt this reuiuing? Thou wert once dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If thou beeſt now aliue, thou maiſt be bolde to conclude, that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2804:33"/> thou art ordained to life; ſeeing thou haſt the beginnings of it already; and ſo much alſo for the power of quickening.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7 <hi>Renewing</hi>
               </note>Laſt of all, the Word hath a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing power: It doth not onely heale, looſe, reuiue, heate, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the ſoules of the Elect, but they are renewed by it; their health, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, life, heate, and comforts, are increaſed daily more and more, they goe on from ſtrength to ſtrength,<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.7.</note> and are daily renewed in the image of their mindes: they renew their ſtrength,<note place="margin">Iſa 40.31.</note> as the Eagles; they are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly edified,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.10.</note> and built vp in their moſt holy faith. And this is done by their purging,<note place="margin">Iude verſe 20</note> through the waſhing of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the Word, and by the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome cloathing,<note place="margin">1 Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and feeding, the word affoords. What ſhall I more ſay? the time would faile me, to ſpeak of all the powers of the word.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:2804:33"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> If the Word hath this renewing power? by this alſo may Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple try, and examine themſelues; doth the Word preached renew thy ſtrength? is it by that thou encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe? doſt thou finde a growth, and going on? yea, an ability to runne without wearineſſe, and to walke without fainting? This may be to thy ſoule an euident ſigne, that thou art or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applica∣tion. </seg>
               </label> You ſee that the Word power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preached, is effectuall in one kinde or other, to ſuch as beare it; and you haue alſo heard the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects of the ſame, of both kindes, in the Elect and reprobate. Know then for concluſion, that if we that are Preachers, perceiue not the manifeſt effects of the powerfull Word in your conuerſion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2804:34"/> you are in danger to feele its power, to your deſtruction and condemnation: It will be either the ſauour of life, or of death, to all that heare it. Labour then to let it haue its effect, in the ſauing of your ſoules: ſuffer the words of exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though they pricke, and wound, and kill, and worke ſorrow in your ſoules; yet they will heale, and reuiue, and glad the hearts of all that ſubmit thereunto: yea, this is that meanes which God hath left, as the chiefe meanes, for the ſauing of ſuch as are ordained to life, the word ſhall be powerfull to conuert, and eſtabliſh, and build them all vp in their moſt holy Faith; yea, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them blameleſſe before the preſence of Gods glory with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ioy.</p>
            <p>Beware then of contending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: It is hard kicking againſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2804:34"/> the prickes, dangerous ſtumbling at this ſtone, fearefull falling on this rocke; Men may rage at, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſuch powerfull Preachers,<note place="margin">Reu. 11.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but the word in their mouthes, is like fire,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.14.</note> to conſume all that dare touch them for hurt. Now therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it not, leſt your hearts be har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened, and your conſciences ſeared, by the power thereof; leſt you be more &amp; more tormented by it, and at length bound hand and foot, and deliuered ouer to Satan: yea, caſt into vtter darkeneſſe, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>I deſire to vſe that power I haue receiued to your conuerſion, and edification, and not to deſtruction. Let the Word then pricke you, that it may promote you; let it launce you, that it may looſe you; let it kill you, that it may quicken you; let it bruiſe you, that it may binde you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2804:35"/> vp; let it terrifie you, that it may turne you from all impiety; let it worke ſencibly vpon you for your ſauing, that it worke not inſencibly for your damning. Which GOD grant, and for which I will bow my knees, vnto that moſt powerfull God, that hee will grant you accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the riches of his grace, the power of turning from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan to himſelfe, that you may receiue the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance amongſt them that are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, by faith in Chriſt Ieſus; and that all ſuch as are already tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from death to life, and from the power of darkneſſe, into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt Ieſus, may be daily built vp, and be more and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, in the image of their mindes, and become more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2804:35"/> to Chriſt their glory: and that euen for Ieſus Chriſts ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs now returne thankes to our God, and pray for a bleſsing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what we haue heard,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
